<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Symphony Gate Enforcer — HALT-gate mechanism
  See architecture spec §2.4, §2.8, §5.1
  See Spec 2b: docs/superpowers/specs/2026-04-10-symphony-core-engine-remaining-design.md §2
-->
<gate-enforcer version="0.0.2-alpha.1">
  <status>runtime</status>
  <spec-reference>docs/superpowers/specs/2026-04-10-symphony-core-engine-remaining-design.md#2-gate-enforcer-runtime</spec-reference>

  <mandates>
    <mandate>Gates HALT on failure. Never advisory, never warn-and-continue.</mandate>
    <mandate>YOLO interaction mode does not bypass gates.</mandate>
    <mandate>A workflow with no gates declared passes trivially (empty or absent gates array = PASS).</mandate>
    <mandate>Gate evaluation order matches declaration order in workflow.yaml.</mandate>
    <mandate>The gate enforcer never modifies artifacts. It only reads and evaluates.</mandate>
  </mandates>

  <flow>
    <step n="1" title="Receive invocation">
      <action>Receive phase parameter: "pre-start" or "post-complete"</action>
      <action>Receive workflow.yaml reference from the calling workflow engine</action>
    </step>

    <step n="2" title="Read gate declarations">
      <action>Read the gates.{phase} array from workflow.yaml (gates.pre_start or gates.post_complete)</action>
      <action>If the gates array is empty or the gates key is absent for this phase: return PASS immediately. No gates declared means no checks needed.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="3" title="Evaluate each gate">
      <for-each item="gate" in="gates array">
        <action>Parse the gate condition. Gate conditions are natural-language assertions declared in workflow.yaml.</action>

        <action title="Adaptive gate substitution (§2.8)">
          If this gate is part of the 6-gate review process AND the current story's traces_to field
          has a prefix of IR-, OR-, or SR- (infrastructure requirement), apply the substitution:
          - "QA Tests" becomes "Policy-as-Code Validation (checkov/tfsec/OPA pass)"
          - "Test Automation" becomes "Plan Validation + Drift Checks (terraform plan assertions)"
          - "Test Review" becomes "Policy Review (OPA/Rego coverage)"
          - "Performance Review" becomes "Cost Review + Scaling Validation"
          - "Code Review" stays as "IaC Code Review" (same workflow, IaC expertise expected)
          - "Security Review" stays unchanged
          The substitution changes the evaluation criteria prompt, not the gate structure.
        </action>

        <action title="Evaluate condition">
          Evaluate the gate condition based on its type:
          - File existence: verify the file exists at the declared path
          - Section completeness: read the file, check all required sections are present and non-empty
          - Confidence threshold: check the last self-critique score in checkpoint metadata
          - Approval status: check artifact frontmatter for "approved: true" or equivalent
          - Test passage: verify the relevant test suite produces exit code 0
          - Custom assertion: evaluate the natural-language condition against current project state
        </action>

        <action title="On failure">
          If the condition fails: return FAIL immediately with:
          - gate: the gate name/description from workflow.yaml
          - phase: "pre-start" or "post-complete"
          - reason: a clear explanation of why the gate failed and what needs to be fixed
          Do NOT continue evaluating remaining gates. First failure halts.
        </action>
      </for-each>
    </step>

    <step n="4" title="All gates passed">
      <action>All gates in the array evaluated successfully. Return PASS.</action>
    </step>
  </flow>
</gate-enforcer>
