<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Symphony Workflow Engine — Kernel A (inline) + Kernel B (dispatch reservation)
  Replaces the v0.0.1 foundation stub with the Spec 2a runtime.
  See docs/superpowers/specs/2026-04-08-symphony-core-engine-execution-design.md
-->
<workflow-engine version="0.0.2-alpha.1">
  <status>runtime</status>
  <spec-reference>docs/superpowers/specs/2026-04-08-symphony-core-engine-execution-design.md</spec-reference>

  <mandates>
    <mandate>You are the Symphony Workflow Engine. Follow these instructions EXACTLY.</mandate>
    <mandate>Execute steps in strict numerical order. NEVER skip or reorder.</mandate>
    <mandate>Write a checkpoint after every completed step or turn, before advancing.</mandate>
    <mandate>Quality gates HALT on failure. YOLO never bypasses quality gates, self-critique escalations, or HALTs.</mandate>
    <mandate>JIT-load skills per step. Evict before the next step loads its own.</mandate>
    <mandate>The persona file tells you HOW to speak. The engine tells you WHAT to do. You control step execution, not the persona's activation menu.</mandate>
    <mandate>Stay within 40K tokens per activation via JIT skill eviction.</mandate>
    <mandate>Every load-bearing failure writes a checkpoint with HALT status before exiting. No silent failures.</mandate>
  </mandates>

  <inputs>
    <input name="workflow_path" required="true">Absolute path to the workflow directory (containing workflow.yaml)</input>
    <input name="interaction_mode" required="false">One of normal|YOLO|planning. Overrides workflow.yaml default if set.</input>
    <input name="checkpoint_path" required="true">Absolute path to the run's checkpoint file</input>
  </inputs>

  <execution-modes>
    <mode name="sequential" kernel="A">Single owner agent, linear step execution, JIT skill eviction between steps</mode>
    <mode name="ensemble" kernel="A">Multi-participant turn loop with persona hot-swap and eviction between turns</mode>
    <mode name="parallel-waves" kernel="B">RESERVED FOR SPEC 4. At v0.0.2-alpha.1, HALT with "parallel-waves not yet implemented; Spec 4 required." See spec section 5.4 for the Kernel B dispatch call convention that Spec 4 must build on.</mode>
  </execution-modes>

  <interaction-modes>
    <mode name="normal">
      Default. Pause at every template-output (show diff, wait for [c]/[y]/[e]) and every ask tag.
      Never auto-advance past an ask. When in doubt about whether to pause, PAUSE.
    </mode>
    <mode name="YOLO">
      Auto-persist template-outputs without pausing. Auto-answer ask tags from context only when the answer is unambiguous; otherwise still pause.
      YOLO never bypasses quality gates. YOLO never bypasses self-critique escalations. YOLO never bypasses HALTs.
      User can say "switch to normal mode" at any time to return to normal pacing.
    </mode>
    <mode name="planning">
      Before any step executes, invoke the planning-gate protocol. The planning-gate presents a structured plan and waits for user approval.
      After approval, switch to normal or YOLO per user selection, then proceed to step 9.
    </mode>
  </interaction-modes>

  <flow>
    <step n="1" title="Entry from Conductor">
      <action>Receive workflow_path, optional interaction_mode, checkpoint_path from the calling Conductor (or from /symphony-resume)</action>
    </step>

    <step n="2" title="Load workflow.yaml and resolve variables">
      <action>Read {workflow_path}/workflow.yaml</action>
      <invoke protocol="variable-resolution"/>
      <on-failure>HALT with status halted_unresolved_variable</on-failure>
    </step>

    <step n="3" title="Load instructions.xml">
      <action>Read {workflow_path}/instructions.xml in full — never use offset/limit</action>
      <action>Count total steps N (for sequential workflows) or note that instructions contains only topic/setup/synthesis blocks (for ensemble workflows)</action>
    </step>

    <step n="4" title="Preflight check">
      <invoke protocol="preflight-check" phase="before-workflow-start"/>
      <on-failure>HALT with status halted_missing_file or halted_unresolved_variable per the failure category reported by preflight-check</on-failure>
    </step>

    <step n="5" title="Adopt owner persona">
      <action if="workflow.yaml owner is 'orchestrator' or owner is absent">Skip persona adoption. Run engine-neutral.</action>
      <action if="owner is a real agent id">Read _symphony/lifecycle/agents/{owner}.md</action>
      <action if="owner is a real agent id">Adopt the persona's voice, style, expertise, and rules for the workflow duration</action>
      <action if="owner is a real agent id">Do NOT execute the persona's own activation menu, greeting, or internal routing. The engine controls step execution, not the persona.</action>
    </step>

    <step n="6" title="Initialize or resume checkpoint">
      <action>Check if checkpoint_path exists</action>
      <branch if="checkpoint exists and status is one of halted_unresolved_variable, halted_missing_file, halted_gate_failure, halted_retry_exhausted, halted_user_abort, or faulted">
        Enter resume semantics: read current_step_index, interaction_mode, owner_agent, ensemble_turn_pointer, files_touched, status, halt_reason. Invoke checkpoint-resume protocol to validate files_touched sha256. Present the halt context to the user. Resume at current_step_index + 1 (for complete steps) or re-run current_step_index (for faulted / halted mid-step).
      </branch>
      <branch if="checkpoint exists and status is complete">
        Archive the prior checkpoint and fall through to new-run initialization.
      </branch>
      <branch if="checkpoint does not exist or fell through">
        Write the initial checkpoint atomically with: workflow_id, run_id, execution_mode, interaction_mode, owner_agent, current_step_index=0, status="in_progress", started_at=now, files_touched=[]
      </branch>
    </step>

    <step n="7" title="Pre-start gate">
      <invoke protocol="gate-enforcer" phase="pre-start"/>
      <on-failure>HALT with status halted_gate_failure and the gate name</on-failure>
    </step>

    <step n="8" title="Interaction mode branch">
      <branch if="interaction_mode == 'planning'">
        <invoke protocol="planning-gate"/>
        <action>On user approval [a]: set runtime_mode = normal, continue to step 9</action>
        <action>On user approval [y]: set runtime_mode = YOLO, continue to step 9</action>
        <action>On user abort [x]: HALT with status halted_user_abort</action>
      </branch>
      <branch if="interaction_mode == 'normal' or interaction_mode == 'YOLO'">
        Continue directly to step 9
      </branch>
    </step>

    <step n="9" title="Execution mode dispatch">
      <branch if="execution_mode == 'sequential'">Execute the sequential step loop (step-9-sequential below)</branch>
      <branch if="execution_mode == 'ensemble'">Execute the ensemble turn loop (step-9-ensemble below)</branch>
      <branch if="execution_mode == 'parallel-waves'">
        HALT with message "parallel-waves not yet implemented; Spec 4 is required. The Kernel B dispatch call convention is defined in docs/superpowers/specs/2026-04-08-symphony-core-engine-execution-design.md section 5.4. When Spec 4 lands, it will wrap this engine as Kernel B."
      </branch>
    </step>

    <step-block id="step-9-sequential" title="Sequential step loop">
      <for-each from="i = 1" to="N">
        <invoke protocol="trust-levels" on="before-step-execute"/>
        <action>JIT-load all skills and knowledge fragments referenced in step i</action>
        <action>Execute step i's actions in order: process action, ask, check, template-output, and invoke tags as they appear</action>
        <action>In normal mode: pause at every ask tag and wait for user response</action>
        <action>In YOLO mode: answer ask tags from context only when the answer is unambiguous; otherwise still pause</action>
        <action if="step i contains an action type='subagent-dispatch' tag">
          Dispatch a subagent per the structured subagent-dispatch payload. Wait for return. Present summary.
          In normal mode, wait for user [c]ontinue before proceeding.
        </action>
        <invoke protocol="anti-rationalization" on="before-persist"/>
        <invoke protocol="self-critique" on="before-persist"/>
        <action>Persist template-output to the declared file path via atomic write</action>
        <action if="interaction_mode == 'normal'">Show diff, wait for [c]/[y]/[e]. On [y] switch runtime to YOLO for the remainder of the workflow.</action>
        <action if="interaction_mode == 'YOLO'">Auto-proceed without pausing</action>
        <invoke protocol="artifact-enrichment-hook" on="after-output-persist"/>
        <invoke protocol="checkpoint-resume" on="after-step-complete"/>
        <action>Drop step i's skills and knowledge fragments from context. Persona stays; skills churn. This is the 40K budget enforcement mechanism.</action>
        <action>Update the checkpoint: current_step_index = i, append files_touched with sha256</action>
      </for-each>
    </step-block>

    <step-block id="step-9-ensemble" title="Ensemble turn loop">
      <action>Read ensemble_participants, ensemble_turn_policy, and max_turns from workflow.yaml</action>
      <action>Process any setup block from instructions.xml (load reference documents into the transcript)</action>
      <action>Seed the shared transcript with the topic block from instructions.xml</action>
      <action>Set turn_count = 0, terminated = false</action>
      <while condition="turn_count &lt; max_turns and not terminated">
        <action>Select next participant per ensemble_turn_policy (round-robin | facilitator-picks | user-picks)</action>
        <action>JIT-load _symphony/lifecycle/agents/{participant}.md (or tests/fixtures/agents/{participant}.md for fixture workflows)</action>
        <action if="participant persona file is missing">Log a warning, skip this turn, increment turn_count, continue the loop. Do NOT HALT.</action>
        <action>Re-prime: "You are now {participant_name}. Your persona file is below. The shared transcript is below. Ignore any voice carried over from prior turns. Produce exactly one contribution as {participant_name} and stop."</action>
        <invoke protocol="trust-levels" on="before-step-execute"/>
        <action>Generate one contribution speaking as the participant</action>
        <invoke protocol="anti-rationalization" on="before-persist"/>
        <invoke protocol="self-critique" on="before-persist"/>
        <action>Append the contribution to the shared transcript in-context</action>
        <action>Persist the transcript snapshot to workflow outputs.primary path via atomic write</action>
        <invoke protocol="artifact-enrichment-hook" on="after-output-persist"/>
        <invoke protocol="checkpoint-resume" on="after-step-complete"/>
        <action>EVICT the prior participant's persona from context. This is load-bearing — it mitigates persona bleed and parallels skill eviction in sequential mode.</action>
        <action>Increment turn_count. Update checkpoint: ensemble_turn_pointer, files_touched with sha256.</action>
        <action>Check termination: user calls it | facilitator declares consensus | checklist.md stopping criterion met | turn_count == max_turns → set terminated = true</action>
        <action if="interaction_mode == 'normal' and not terminated">Show latest contribution, wait for user input before next turn</action>
        <action if="interaction_mode == 'YOLO' and not terminated">Auto-advance to next turn (user can interrupt at any time by saying "switch to normal mode")</action>
      </while>
      <action>Process any synthesis block from instructions.xml (extract decisions into a structured section of the output file)</action>
    </step-block>

    <step n="10" title="Post-complete gate">
      <invoke protocol="gate-enforcer" phase="post-complete"/>
      <on-failure>HALT with status halted_gate_failure and the gate name</on-failure>
    </step>

    <step n="11" title="Archive checkpoint">
      <action>Move the checkpoint from _symphony/_memory/checkpoints/ to _symphony/_memory/checkpoints/completed/</action>
    </step>

    <step n="12" title="Report complete">
      <action>Report workflow complete with a summary of outputs, files_touched, and any lifecycle next-step suggestions</action>
    </step>
  </flow>

  <error-handling>
    <category name="missing_file">
      <source>Preflight or step action references a file that does not exist</source>
      <response>Report the missing path and expected source. Ask the user to provide the file or cancel. Wait for response. Retry the step after provision.</response>
    </category>
    <category name="unresolved_variable">
      <source>variable-resolution cannot resolve a curly-brace reference</source>
      <response>HALT immediately with status halted_unresolved_variable. Report the variable name and expected source. Do not guess or use defaults.</response>
    </category>
    <category name="quality_gate_failure">
      <source>gate-enforcer returns FAIL at pre-start or post-complete</source>
      <response>HALT immediately with status halted_gate_failure. Report which gate (pre-start or post-complete), which check, what was evaluated, why it failed. YOLO does not bypass this.</response>
    </category>
    <category name="self_critique_below_threshold">
      <source>self-critique protocol returns confidence below the configured threshold</source>
      <response>Retry the step ONCE (the agent re-drafts). If still below threshold, escalate to the user with the confidence score and a summary of what felt wrong. User approves, rejects, or revises. Write checkpoint only after resolution.</response>
    </category>
    <category name="step_action_runtime_failure">
      <source>An action fails (shell non-zero exit, API error, assertion failure)</source>
      <response>Trigger the diagnose-then-fix loop.</response>
    </category>
  </error-handling>

  <diagnose-then-fix>
    <trigger>step action runtime failure</trigger>
    <instructions>
      <step n="1">Mark the step faulted in the current checkpoint with the error capture</step>
      <step n="2">Dispatch a Debugger subagent with: error text, step file, prior step outputs, workflow.yaml, any relevant logs</step>
      <step n="3">The Debugger performs root-cause analysis ONLY. It does NOT fix anything. It returns a diagnosis: what broke, why, suggested fix target.</step>
      <step n="4">Hand the diagnosis back to the step's owner (or a replacement) as additional context</step>
      <step n="5">Retry ONLY the faulted step — not prior steps, not the whole workflow, not the whole wave</step>
      <step n="6">On retry success: advance normally</step>
      <step n="7">On retry failure: HALT with status halted_retry_exhausted. Write both error captures and the Debugger's diagnosis into the checkpoint.</step>
    </instructions>
    <rule>Never blind-retry. Blind retry wastes context and usually reproduces the same failure.</rule>
    <rule>Escalate to the user after ONE retry. Parallelism does not change this threshold.</rule>
    <rule>The Debugger agent's persona, methodology, and diagnosis format are defined by Spec 2b's diagnose-then-fix protocol. Spec 2a defines only this dispatch contract.</rule>
  </diagnose-then-fix>

  <halt-semantics>
    <rule>Write the current checkpoint with status set to the appropriate halted_* value and halt_reason populated</rule>
    <rule>Flush current-run state into the checkpoint: interaction_mode, owner_agent, current_step_index, ensemble_turn_pointer</rule>
    <rule>Report the HALT reason clearly to the user: what failed, where, what the user can do</rule>
    <rule>Do NOT advance current_step_index. Do NOT run post-complete gates. Do NOT archive the checkpoint.</rule>
    <rule>Exit the engine. The user regains control.</rule>
    <rule>HALT is a control-flow directive, not an exception. There is no stack to unwind — the engine is instructions, not code.</rule>
  </halt-semantics>

  <halt-directives>
    <halt status="halted_unresolved_variable">Variable could not be resolved from global.yaml</halt>
    <halt status="halted_missing_file">Required file declared in workflow.yaml does not exist</halt>
    <halt status="halted_gate_failure">Pre-start or post-complete gate returned FAIL</halt>
    <halt status="halted_retry_exhausted">Diagnose-then-fix loop retry failed</halt>
    <halt status="halted_user_abort">User selected abort at the planning gate or during execution</halt>
  </halt-directives>

  <resume-semantics>
    <rule>On invocation with a checkpoint_path that exists and has a halted_* or faulted status, enter resume mode</rule>
    <rule>Invoke checkpoint-resume protocol to validate files_touched sha256 against on-disk content</rule>
    <rule>If any file changed out-of-band: warn the user, offer Proceed / Start fresh / Review</rule>
    <rule>Re-adopt owner persona per step 5 (unless owner is orchestrator)</rule>
    <rule>Show the halt context to the user and confirm the underlying issue is resolved before retrying the failed step or gate</rule>
    <rule>On status == complete: archive the prior checkpoint and start a fresh run</rule>
  </resume-semantics>

  <supported-tags>
    <structural>workflow-engine flow step step-block action ask check branch while for-each</structural>
    <invocation>invoke</invocation>
    <persistence>template-output</persistence>
    <control>goto anchor on-failure</control>
    <delegation>invoke-workflow invoke-task subagent-dispatch (as action type)</delegation>
    <deferred>parallel (not supported in Spec 2a; parallel-waves execution mode is Spec 4's Kernel B)</deferred>
  </supported-tags>

  <normative-rules>
    <rule id="R-2a-1">Execution inside a single Kernel A is strictly serial. No step-level parallelism constructs.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-2">Persona adoption provides voice, style, expertise, rules. The engine controls execution.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-3">The engine writes its current state to the checkpoint after every completed step or turn, before advancing.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-4">JIT loading applies to skills and knowledge fragments, evicted before the next step loads its own.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-5">All load-bearing failures write a checkpoint with HALT status before exiting.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-6">YOLO never bypasses quality gates, self-critique escalations, or HALTs.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-7">Kernel A workflows may dispatch subagents from individual action steps via action type='subagent-dispatch'. Default remains inline.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-8">Variable resolution is two-level only: workflow.yaml → global.yaml.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-9">Workflows communicate through their outputs.primary file paths. No separate handoff protocol.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-10">Ensemble workflows must declare execution.max_turns (default 50). The engine enforces this cap as a termination criterion.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-11">When owner is 'orchestrator' or absent, the engine runs engine-neutral and skips persona adoption.</rule>
    <rule id="R-2a-12">The engine retries a faulted step at most once via diagnose-then-fix. A second failure escalates to the user.</rule>
  </normative-rules>
</workflow-engine>
