<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Symphony Engine-Internal Protocol: planning-gate
  Owned by Spec 2a. Engine-internal — not a cross-cutting protocol.
  Invoked only when interaction_mode is "planning".
  See docs/superpowers/specs/2026-04-08-symphony-core-engine-execution-design.md section 5.1 step 8
-->
<protocol name="planning-gate" version="0.0.2-alpha.1">
  <objective>
    Present a structured execution plan to the user before any workflow
    step runs. Collect user approval or abort. Return the runtime
    interaction mode (normal or YOLO) that the engine should use after
    approval.
  </objective>

  <mandates>
    <mandate>Invoked only when interaction_mode == "planning"</mandate>
    <mandate>Parse instructions.xml into a structured plan — do not execute any step</mandate>
    <mandate>Present the plan in fixed section order for predictability</mandate>
    <mandate>Wait for user selection: a (normal) | y (YOLO) | r (revise) | x (abort)</mandate>
    <mandate>Never auto-approve. The user must explicitly select a or y.</mandate>
  </mandates>

  <plan-sections>
    <section name="Context">High-level goal statement from the workflow's description, the owner agent, the declared inputs, and the expected outputs</section>
    <section name="Files to Modify">Every file path the plan will write to, extracted from step template-output declarations</section>
    <section name="Detailed Edits">One line per step: step number, title, what the step produces, which skills it JIT-loads</section>
    <section name="Implementation Order">The strict numerical step order as declared in instructions.xml</section>
    <section name="Verification">Which gates fire pre-start and post-complete, which cross-cutting disciplines are invoked</section>
  </plan-sections>

  <flow>
    <step n="1" title="Parse instructions for plan content">
      <action>Read the already-loaded instructions.xml content</action>
      <action>Extract each step's number, title, actions, template-output (if any), skill references</action>
      <action>Extract gate declarations from workflow.yaml</action>
      <action>Build the five Plan Sections listed above</action>
    </step>
    <step n="2" title="Present plan">
      <action>Render the plan sections to the user in fixed order: Context, Files to Modify, Detailed Edits, Implementation Order, Verification</action>
      <action>Omit any section that is empty (e.g., a workflow with no template-outputs has no Files to Modify)</action>
    </step>
    <step n="3" title="Collect user decision">
      <action>Display prompt: "[a] Approve (normal) | [y] Approve (YOLO) | [r] Revise plan | [x] Abort"</action>
      <action>Wait for user selection</action>
    </step>
    <step n="4" title="Handle decision">
      <action if="user selects [a]">Return runtime_mode = normal. Engine proceeds to step 9 of workflow flow.</action>
      <action if="user selects [y]">Return runtime_mode = YOLO. Engine proceeds to step 9 of workflow flow.</action>
      <action if="user selects [r]">Ask user for feedback on the plan. Regenerate plan incorporating feedback. Re-present via step 2.</action>
      <action if="user selects [x]">HALT the workflow with status halted_user_abort. Write checkpoint with abort reason.</action>
    </step>
  </flow>
</protocol>
